<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><search><entry><title>Introducing Simple7702Account and Universal7702Account: EIP-7702 Smart Account Implementations</title><url>/post/introducing-simple7702account-and-universal7702account/</url><categories><category>Solidity</category><category>Defi</category><category>EIP-7702</category></categories><tags><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>EIP-7702</tag><tag>Simple7702Account</tag><tag>Universal7702Account</tag></tags><content type="html">  Introducing Simple7702Account and Universal7702Account: EIP-7702 Smart Account Implementations The Ethereum ecosystem is evolving rapidly, and EIP-7702 represents one of the most significant upgrades to account abstraction. In this post, we&amp;amp;rsquo;ll explore two production-ready implementations: Simple7702Account and Universal7702Account, designed to bring smart contract functionality to Externally Owned Accounts (EOAs).
Why This Project? In typical scenarios—such as facilitating simple transfers for custodial wallet users—the existing ERC-4337 paymaster solutions present significant challenges:
Overly Complex: ERC-4337 requires a full bundler infrastructure, entry point contracts, and complex paymaster logic Third-Party Dependencies: Many solutions rely on external services like Pimlico, Alchemy, or other infrastructure providers High Integration Cost: Setting up and maintaining the entire 4337 stack is resource-intensive For many use cases, you don&amp;amp;rsquo;t need the full power of …  </content></entry><entry><title>Centralized exchanges and wallets should take the lead in using Account abstraction</title><url>/post/centrals-instructions-should-using-account-abstraction/</url><categories><category>web3</category><category>crypto</category></categories><tags><tag>web3</tag><tag>account abstraction</tag><tag>crypto</tag><tag>Etheruem</tag></tags><content type="html">  Centralized exchanges and wallets should take the lead in using Account abstraction
Currently, when centralized exchanges and wallets process user tokens, the usual practices are as follows:
Assign an address to each user; When the user transfers currency to a changed address, transfer a small amount of main chain tokens (ETH, BNB, TRX, etc) to the changed address. Transfer the user token to the fund collection address of the exchange or wallet This approach has some disadvantages:
The operation is complicated The private key of each address needs to be strictly managed. Fund collection requires a main chain token to be transferred to each address first as gas fee, and then funds can be collected. Each address collection requires a transaction, and transactions cannot be merged. Therefore, centralized exchanges and wallets can consider using Account Abstraction accounts as user addresses. This approach has several advantages:
Convenient collection. a. When creating an account, use the approve method to transfer the token transfer permission of the address to the collection address; b. You can transfer funds from multiple accounts in one transaction through contract methods, improving efficiency and saving gas at the same time; The main disadvantage of this method is that when creating an AA account for the first time, a gas fee is required.
  </content></entry><entry><title>Make JWT more safe</title><url>/post/make-jwt-more-safe/</url><categories><category>JWT</category></categories><tags><tag>JWT</tag><tag>safety</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  What is JWT JSON Web Token (JWT) is an open standard (RFC 7519) that defines a compact and self-contained way for securely transmitting information between parties as a JSON object. This information can be verified and trusted because it is digitally signed. JWTs can be signed using a secret (with the HMAC algorithm) or a public/private key pair using RSA or ECDSA.
Make JWT more safe secret for every Account In some best practice of JWT, they just say we need an universe secret for every account signature, which mostly from an envirment varible. But the secret is so fundemental, is it enough safe that a global secret for all account? Nobody care it, nobody discuss it, nobody mention it.
We use different salt to hash account password for different account, why we use same secret for all account? The JWT is JUST as important as user&rsquo;s password!
In my opinion, we should use different secret for every account, just like password salt.
If we use different secret for every account, we should save the secret in server side, DB or redis. Of course, this will slow down the JWT validate flow, but we could save the secret in server&rsquo;s memory cache after server start up.
save &amp; validate signature in server side JWT is mostly about how to verify the JWT token is valid, by the signature. In most scene, this is great. But in some case, for example, we want kick off a special user, JWT can do nothing.
So, we could save the JWT signature in the server, then we could verify the JWT twice:
first, verify the signature; second, check the signature in server DB or redis, if exists, the JWT is valid; or else invalid By this method, we can kick off user or force user re-login.
Also, there are some tricks, we don&rsquo;t need to save all JWT payload in the server, for example, we can just save the userId and JWT signature in the server side.
JWT for anonymous or visitors Sometime we want give better user expirence for the anonymous or visitors, we can use JWT to record visitor&rsquo;s information. For example, the user&rsquo;s information:
1 2 3 4 name IP address first visit time location(optional) use these information, we could track visitors and provide good expirence.
Question If we use JWT this way, why we use JWT instead of session? One of the most benefit of JWT is the client can get many information from JWT, even they have not connect to the server.
  ]]></content></entry><entry><title>A Little Thought on Stablecoins (1)</title><url>/post/thinking/permissionless-lending/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>Solidity</category><category>lending</category><category>algo-stablecoin</category></categories><tags><tag>defi</tag><tag>lending</tag><tag>stablecoin</tag></tags><content type="html">  Since the COVID-19 outbreak in 2019, we have seen all kinds of de-globalization trends and new restrictions. After the war in Ukraine, people also began to question the ongoing de-globalization of finance. Can the US dollar still be trusted? Can the financial institutions of neutral countries still be trusted? Behind all of these trust crises is a deeper signal: decentralized assets such as BTC and ETH point toward a better long-term direction for humanity.
We are standing at the crossroads of a major transformation.
On Power Before talking about stablecoins, we need to talk about power.
Most current regulation aimed at crypto is only the surface. At its core, it is a struggle over power. Power naturally reinforces and expands itself. Today, most power is concentrated in the hands of politicians and the wealthy. That is why governments keep expanding their reach, while wealth becomes more concentrated in every country.
As blockchains increasingly penetrate finance and the broader …  </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE v3 Key Features</title><url>/post/aave/aave-v3-features/</url><categories><category>defi</category><category>aave</category><category>lending</category></categories><tags><tag>aave</tag><tag>defi</tag><tag>lending</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  The AAVE v3 codebase had already been audited and was close to release when this post was written. This version focused mainly on several themes:
capital efficiency risk-control strategy decentralization cross-chain support The AAVE v3 contracts are open source:
https://github.com/aave/aave-v3-core Let&rsquo;s look at the major improvements this release introduced.
Features Compared with AAVE V2, the main features of V3 are:
Portal eMode Isolation Mode improved risk management L2-focused capabilities community contributions Technical Progress Driven by Community Feedback Although the Aave protocol had already worked well and grown significantly over the previous two years, community feedback played a very important role in driving AAVE forward:
Capital efficiency: V2 did not let users optimize supplied assets as effectively, whether in terms of yield generation within or across protocols and networks, or in terms of borrowing power. V3 addresses that.
Risk-control tuning: The Aave protocol already had risk parameters that governance could adjust, such as borrowing power and safety margins, but additional mechanisms could improve the protocol&rsquo;s built-in security assumptions. V3 addresses that too.
Decentralization: Aave governance was already active and healthy, with community proposals and the creation of sub-DAOs such as GrantsDAO and RiskDAO. But some additional technical features make it possible to decentralize even more functionality through delegation.
Cross-chain: Through community effort, Aave had been deployed to many networks, each with its own pool of liquidity. But users could not move their personal liquidity seamlessly from one network to another. V3 addresses that.
V3 was designed to become the next generation of base-layer DeFi infrastructure, significantly improving user experience while also delivering higher capital efficiency, stronger decentralization, and better security.
Portal Portal diagram:
Portal allows users to move assets seamlessly across multiple networks. For example, a user can burn aTokens on Ethereum and mint them on Polygon. Conceptually this is similar to other cross-chain liquidity mechanisms, though the underlying technical design deserves a deeper look.
eMode eMode diagram:
A simple example: under eMode, if you supply wBTC and only borrow renBTC, your LTV can go as high as 97%, the liquidation threshold can be 98%, and the liquidation penalty can be 2%. In other words, when users borrow within a tightly correlated asset category, capital efficiency goes up while risk goes down.
The underlying idea is to group assets into categories. There can be up to 255 categories.
For example, one category may contain stablecoins such as USDT, USDC, and DAI. In that mode, a user who supplies USDC and borrows DAI may get an LTV of 97%, whereas the normal mode might only allow 75%. That immediately increases capital efficiency by 22 percentage points.
Of course, users can still supply assets outside the chosen category, but those assets only receive the normal-mode LTV treatment.
New Risk-Management Parameters Isolation Mode
The goal of Isolation Mode is to reduce risk when governance lists new assets on Aave.
When the community submits a governance proposal to list a new asset, that asset can be marked as &ldquo;isolated collateral&rdquo;. Users who supply isolated assets as collateral are only allowed to borrow governance-approved stablecoins, and their borrow amount is capped by a protocol-defined debt ceiling.
When a user supplies an isolated asset as collateral, that asset is the only collateral they may use. Even if the user also supplies other assets to the protocol, those additional assets only earn interest and cannot be used as collateral.
Bug Bounty and RiskDAO RiskDAO: https://governance.aave.com/t/proposal-aave-risk-dao/4729 Other Features Token-transfer-related functions such as supply and repay support EIP-2612 permits, which is especially useful on L2. The protocol supports EIP-712 signatures. Users can repay debt using aTokens instead of only the original borrowed asset. Aave governance can permit-list specific entities for instant liquidity access. Aave governance can reconfigure fees charged for liquidations or instant-liquidity transactions, directing them to the Aave DAO treasury. The new flashloanSimple path can reduce gas usage by up to 20%, while the full-featured standard flash-loan function remains available. Oracle logic can now support more general base-asset calculations and is no longer limited to ETH-denominated assumptions. The new interest-rate strategy optimizes stable-rate calculation and no longer requires a lending-rate oracle. The codebase has been restructured into more modular repositories. Compared with the monolithic V2 repository, V3 is split into v3-core, v3-periphery, and v3-deployments, which helps community contributions and multi-network deployment. Smart contracts were refactored to reduce code size, leaving more room for future upgrades and allowing optimizer settings up to 100K runs. Even with all of these new features, the overall gas cost still decreased by roughly 10% to 15%.
Code-Level Impressions Note: this section reflects my quick first impression after browsing V3.
Gas optimization
Solidity was upgraded to 0.8.10. Several core math components were rewritten, and much more assembly is used to save gas.
New functionality
eMode isolation mode Naming changes
For example:
deposit was renamed to supply LendingPool.sol was renamed to Pool.sol core business logic was moved further into libraries/logic, including the new eMode, isolation, and bridge logic Peripheral functionality moved into separate repositories
Similar to Uniswap, there is a dedicated periphery repository. Deployments also appear to live in a separate repository. When installing aave-v3-core, one dependency named @aave/deploy-v3 is pulled in, but at the time of writing it was not easy to locate directly. Related issue: https://github.com/aave/aave-v3-core/issues/625 Protocol licensing changes
If you are planning to fork AAVE v3, note that its licensing appears more similar to Uniswap v3. See: https://github.com/aave/aave-v3-core/blob/master/LICENSE.md In practice, though, most projects still fork Compound far more often than AAVE.
The core architecture has not changed dramatically
References https://governance.aave.com/t/introducing-aave-v3/6035 https://github.com/aave/aave-v3-core   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>Using Lua Scripts for Redis Transactions</title><url>/post/2021-11/redis-lua-script-transaction/</url><categories><category>redis</category></categories><tags><tag>redis</tag><tag>lua script</tag><tag>transcation</tag><tag>consistency</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  Redis transactions can be implemented in two ways: with MULTI, or with Lua scripts. Lua scripts are simpler, require fewer client-server interactions, and can be cached by Redis, which makes them especially useful in performance-sensitive scenarios.
Lua Scripts Official documentation: https://redis.io/commands/eval Redis provides two commands for executing Lua scripts: eval and evalsha.
The syntax of eval is:
1 2 3 4 5 6 &gt; eval &#34;return {KEYS[1],KEYS[2],ARGV[1],ARGV[2], ARGV[3]}&#34; 2 key1 key2 first second third 1) &#34;key1&#34; 2) &#34;key2&#34; 3) &#34;first&#34; 4) &#34;second&#34; 5) &#34;third&#34; Explanation:
The second string argument is the Lua script itself. KEYS and ARGV are reserved keywords. 2 means the script references two keys. KEYS is used to pass Redis keys into the script. ARGV contains the remaining arguments after the keys, indexed from 1. return specifies the returned value. If the server has already cached the Lua script, you can use evalsha instead. This reduces payload size when the script body is large.
Starting from Redis 3.2.0, Redis also ships with a Lua debugger: https://redis.io/topics/ldb Example 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 import &#34;github.com/gomodule/redigo/redis&#34; // Redis Lua script that guarantees atomic reservation when allocating multiple IDs. func ReserveUserToken(conn redis.Conn, accountID uint64, howmany uint32) (latest uint64, err error) { ss := `local sid=redis.call(&#39;HGET&#39;,KEYS[1],&#39;latest&#39;) or 0; ` for i := 0; i &lt; int(howmany); i++ { ss += `redis.call(&#39;HSET&#39;, KEYS[1], sid, ARGV[1]); sid=sid+1; ` } // Update latest ss += `redis.call(&#39;HSET&#39;, KEYS[1], &#39;latest&#39;, sid); return sid` script := redis.NewScript(1, ss) key := fmt.Sprintf(&#34;userTokens:%d&#34;, accountID) ts := time.Now().Unix() resp, err := script.Do(conn, key, ts) if err != nil { return } latest = uint64(resp.(int64)) return } This code works as follows:
It creates a Redis hash named userToken:{accountId} for each user if it does not already exist, and initializes the latest field to 0. If howmany is not zero, it reserves that many tokens for the user by: incrementing latest and using the new value as the hash field writing the reserved timestamp into the hash repeating this in a loop It writes the final latest value back to the hash and returns it. One important detail is the trailing or 0 in local sid=redis.call('HGET',KEYS[1],'latest') or 0;. Without it, sid may become a boolean value when the field does not exist, and arithmetic on it will fail with an error like this:
1 (error) ERR Error running script (call to f_2bd1a2e80fc04313100937b7b533da6bea026773): @user_script:1: user_script:1: attempt to perform arithmetic on local &#39;sid&#39; (a boolean value) Additional Notes Lua conditionals The syntax for conditionals in Lua is:
1 2 3 4 5 if cond then clause else clause end Without an else, it can be shortened to:
1 2 3 if cond then clause end Lua also supports elseif.
Integers and strings Redis keys are strings, while values can be integers. If your key itself looks numeric and you compare it directly with an integer value, you may get unexpected results because the key is still a string. If you need numeric comparison, use one of these approaches:
Convert with tonumber Force conversion with +0 JSON handling Lua scripts inside Redis have the cjson library built in, so you can use cjson.encode and cjson.decode directly.
An encode example:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 local user={name=ARGV[1],year=ARGV[2],address=ARGV[3]}; local userJson=cjson.encode(user); if redis.call(&#39;HSET&#39;, &#39;users&#39;, ARGV[1], userJson) == 0 then return -1 else return userJson end decode is similar:
1 2 local userJson = redis.call(&#39;HSET&#39;, &#39;users&#39;, ARGV[1]); local user = cjson.decode(userJson)   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>Common Hardhat and Solidity Errors</title><url>/post/hardhat/hardhat-solidity-common-cases/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>Solidity</category></categories><tags><tag>hardhat</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>hardhat-deploy</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  Common hardhat Issues This is a growing list of common Hardhat and Solidity errors I have run into.
hardhat-deploy: cannot find artifact &ldquo;xxxx&rdquo; There are usually two possible causes:
The contract really does not exist. There are duplicate contract definitions. The first case is usually easy to spot. The second is harder to notice because the error message is misleading. If you see this error, make sure there are no duplicate contract definitions in the project.
Error: Cannot find module 'typechain/dist/TypeChain' Cause: this happens when you are using the old hardhat-typechain package, which is no longer maintained.
Fix:
Remove the hardhat-typechain dependency. Add typechain, @typechain/hardhat, and @typechain/ethers-v5. 1 yarn add -D typechain @typechain/hardhat @typechain/ethers-v5 Update hardhat.config.ts: 1 2 - import &#39;hardhat-typechain&#39;; + import &#39;@typechain/hardhat&#39; https://github.com/dethcrypto/TypeChain/issues/409   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>Critical UUPS Proxy Vulnerability in OpenZeppelin 4.1.0-4.3.1</title><url>/post/contract-proxy/uups-proxy-vulunerability/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>Solidity</category><category>Security</category></categories><tags><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>Proxy</tag><tag>vulunerability</tag><tag>openzeppelin</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  OpenZeppelin supports two main proxy patterns:
Transparent proxy UUPS proxy The most important difference is where the upgradeTo logic lives. In a transparent proxy, the upgrade logic is implemented in the proxy contract. In a UUPS proxy, the upgrade logic lives in the implementation contract.
The Vulnerability OpenZeppelin&rsquo;s upgradeable system is usually composed of multiple contracts. Each upgradeable deployment includes an implementation contract that contains the business logic and a proxy contract that stores the state. Upgrading the proxy simply means changing the proxy&rsquo;s implementation pointer to a new implementation contract.
Upgrade flow diagram:
In versions 4.1.0 through 4.3.1, the upgradeTo function on UUPSUpgradeable did not restrict who could call it. That meant anyone could call it directly on the implementation contract. An attacker could deploy a malicious contract whose upgradeTo path executes SELFDESTRUCT, then call upgradeTo on the implementation contract and point it to the malicious contract. The result is that the implementation destroys itself. One crucial detail is that calling SELFDESTRUCT here does not cause the transaction to fail. Once the implementation code is gone, the proxy loses its logic and the whole system breaks.
The older implementation of upgradeTo was:
1 2 3 4 function upgradeTo(address newImplementation) external virtual { _authorizeUpgrade(newImplementation); _upgradeToAndCallSecure(newImplementation, bytes(&#34;&#34;), false); } In version 4.3.2 it became:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 modifier onlyProxy() { require(address(this) != __self, &#34;Function must be called through delegatecall&#34;); require(_getImplementation() == __self, &#34;Function must be called through active proxy&#34;); _; } function upgradeTo(address newImplementation) external virtual onlyProxy { _authorizeUpgrade(newImplementation); _upgradeToAndCallSecure(newImplementation, new bytes(0), false); } Now upgradeTo on the implementation can only be executed through the active proxy.
How upgradeTo Works in the UUPS Pattern The deployment process for a UUPS system is roughly:
First, deploy the implementation contract. It must inherit from ERC1967UpgradeUpgradeable.
Second, deploy the ERC1967Proxy contract and initialize it with the implementation address from the previous step.
Finally, use the proxy to call upgradeTo.
The relevant code looks like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 function upgradeTo(address newImplementation) external virtual onlyProxy { _authorizeUpgrade(newImplementation); _upgradeToAndCallSecure(newImplementation, new bytes(0), false); } function _upgradeToAndCallSecure( address newImplementation, bytes memory data, bool forceCall ) internal { address oldImplementation = _getImplementation(); // Initial upgrade and setup call _setImplementation(newImplementation); if (data.length &gt; 0 || forceCall) { _functionDelegateCall(newImplementation, data); } // Perform rollback test if not already in progress StorageSlotUpgradeable.BooleanSlot storage rollbackTesting = StorageSlotUpgradeable.getBooleanSlot(_ROLLBACK_SLOT); if (!rollbackTesting.value) { // Trigger rollback using upgradeTo from the new implementation rollbackTesting.value = true; _functionDelegateCall( newImplementation, abi.encodeWithSignature(&#34;upgradeTo(address)&#34;, oldImplementation) ); rollbackTesting.value = false; // Check rollback was effective require(oldImplementation == _getImplementation(), &#34;ERC1967Upgrade: upgrade breaks further upgrades&#34;); // Finally reset to the new implementation and log the upgrade _upgradeTo(newImplementation); } } function _upgradeTo(address newImplementation) internal { _setImplementation(newImplementation); emit Upgraded(newImplementation); } function _setImplementation(address newImplementation) private { require(AddressUpgradeable.isContract(newImplementation), &#34;ERC1967: new implementation is not a contract&#34;); StorageSlotUpgradeable.getAddressSlot(_IMPLEMENTATION_SLOT).value = newImplementation; } Here, _authorizeUpgrade is the permission check implemented by the application contract. Any contract inheriting from ERC1967UpgradeUpgradeable must provide this function, and in practice it usually restricts upgrades to the owner.
Inside _upgradeToAndCallSecure, the new implementation is subjected to a rollback test. The contract temporarily delegates into the new implementation and asks it to upgrade back to the old implementation. This verifies that the new implementation&rsquo;s upgrade logic is still functional and that future upgrades will remain possible.
If that rollback test succeeds, the contract finally stores the new implementation address in _IMPLEMENTATION_SLOT.
https://forum.openzeppelin.com/t/uupsupgradeable-vulnerability-post-mortem/15680   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: Deployment and Initialization</title><url>/post/aave/how-aave-deploy-and-initialize-contracts/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>deploy</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>initialize</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  Because AAVE contains many contracts, its deployment process is correspondingly complex. AAVE splits deployment into seven tasks, each implemented as a hardhat task, and then uses a full task to orchestrate deployment and initialization end to end.
Full task Inside package.json, the project defines many deployment commands. The following one deploys to mainnet and verifies contracts:
1 &#34;aave:main:full:migration&#34;: &#34;npm run compile &amp;&amp; npm run hardhat:main -- aave:mainnet --verify&#34;, Here, aave:mainnet is the task name, and it is defined in tasks/migrations/aave.mainnet.ts. The main body looks like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 // 1 Deploy address-provider-related contracts, POOL_NAME is Aave await DRE.run(&#39;full:deploy-address-provider&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME, skipRegistry }); // 2 Deploy lending-pool-related contracts await DRE.run(&#39;full:deploy-lending-pool&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); // 3 Deploy oracle-related contracts await DRE.run(&#39;full:deploy-oracles&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); // 4 Deploy data-provider-related contracts await DRE.run(&#39;full:data-provider&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); // 5 Deploy WETH gateway await DRE.run(&#39;full-deploy-weth-gateway&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); // 6 Initialize related contracts await DRE.run(&#39;full:initialize-lending-pool&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); if (verify) { printContracts(); // 7 Verify contracts await DRE.run(&#39;verify:general&#39;, { all: true, pool: POOL_NAME }); // 8 Verify aToken and debt token contracts await DRE.run(&#39;verify:tokens&#39;, { pool: POOL_NAME }); } if (usingTenderly()) { } // Print deployed contract info printContracts(); Now let&rsquo;s look at what each task does.
1. full:deploy-address-provider Task name: full:deploy-address-provider
Task file: tasks/full/1_address_provider.ts
Purpose: deploy the address registry and address provider
Execution flow:
deploy LendingPoolAddressesProvider with marketId such as Aave or AMM run the add-market-to-registry task if the registry does not exist, deploy LendingPoolAddressesProviderRegistry call registerAddressesProvider call setPoolAdmin call setEmergencyAdmin 2. full:deploy-lending-pool Task name: full:deploy-lending-pool
Task file: tasks/full/2_lending_pool.ts
Purpose: deploy the lending pool and related contracts
Execution flow:
if LendingPool is not yet deployed, deploy the related libraries and the LendingPool implementation, then initialize it use the address provider created in step 1 to deploy a proxy for LendingPool, and point that proxy to the LendingPool implementation deploy LendingPoolConfigurator call addressesProvider.setLendingPoolConfiguratorImpl, which deploys a proxy for LendingPoolConfigurator and stores that address in the provider deploy StableAndVariableTokensHelper deploy ATokensAndRatesHelper 3. full:deploy-oracles Task name: full:deploy-oracles
Task file: tasks/full/3_oracles.ts
Purpose: deploy oracle contracts
Execution flow:
if AaveOracle does not exist, deploy it and call setAssetSources if LendingRateOracle does not exist, deploy it and initialize it through setInitialMarketRatesInRatesOracleByHelper set addressesProvider.setPriceOracle to the deployed AaveOracle set addressesProvider.setLendingRateOracle to the deployed LendingRateOracle 4. full:data-provider Task name: full:data-provider
Task file: tasks/full/4_data-provider.ts
Purpose: deploy data-provider contracts
Execution flow:
deploy AaveProtocolDataProvider 5. WETH gateway contract Task name: full-deploy-weth-gateway
Task file: tasks/full/5-deploy-wethGateWay.ts
Purpose: deploy WETHGateway
Execution flow:
deploy WETHGateway 6. Initialize contracts Task name: full:initialize-lending-pool
Task file: tasks/full/6-initialize.ts
Purpose: deploy contracts, set proxies, and initialize the system
Execution flow:
initReservesByHelper: for each token in the market, do the following: deploy AToken deploy StableDebtToken deploy VariableDebtToken deploy DefaultReserveInterestRateStrategy call LendingPoolConfigurator to deploy proxies for aToken and debt tokens, then initialize them configureReservesByHelper if LendingPoolCollateralManager does not exist, deploy it set the LendingPoolCollateralManager address in addressesProvider deploy WalletBalanceProvider, a read-only helper that exposes aggregated data configure the WETHGateway 7. Contract verification Verification is mostly done through hardhat-etherscan.
AToken / debtToken AToken, VariableDebtToken, and StableDebtToken all run behind proxies. Their proxy pattern is somewhat similar to OpenZeppelin&rsquo;s transparent proxy model.
LendingPoolConfigurator is the creator and manager of those aToken and debt-token proxies, and is also responsible for initializing and upgrading them.
At the same time, LendingPoolConfigurator itself sits behind a proxy created by AddressProvider, and upgrades are managed through AddressProvider.
  ]]></content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: Flash Loans</title><url>/post/aave/aave-flashloan/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Compound</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>flashloan</tag><tag>flash-loan</tag></tags><content type="html">  Flash Loans A flash loan is a loan that is borrowed and repaid within a single transaction, without collateral. The key is that everything happens inside one transaction. Because repayment happens in the same transaction, no collateral is required. The blockchain can verify whether the repayment amount is greater than or equal to the principal plus interest. If it is not, the whole transaction reverts and all state changes are rolled back. In other words, the borrowed funds are rolled back too, so the lender takes no risk.
Flash loans can also generate meaningful fee income. A single block only lasts a few seconds, yet the protocol can charge 9 basis points. In practice, flash loans are often used with very large position sizes, easily tens or even hundreds of millions of dollars.
Flash loans are one of the most important innovations in DeFi. I am not sure whether AAVE was the first protocol to introduce them, but today many protocols support them. For example:
Lending protocols such as AAVE and Compound can support flash loans directly or through extensions. AAVE&amp;rsquo;s default flash-loan fee is 9 basis points. Uniswap also enables a flash-loan-like flow during swaps. The pair contract sends you the output tokens first, you use them for your strategy, and then you transfer the input tokens back to the pair. Uniswap does not charge an extra flash-loan fee, only the normal swap fee. Some tokens also implement flash-loan functionality using similar ideas. The fee depends on the implementation. Flash Loan Flow The flow is roughly:
Validate the parameters with ValidationLogic.validateFlashloan. Calculate the premium and transfer the tokens to the user. Call the user contract so it can execute its logic. Add the premium and transfer principal plus fee back from the user contract. If the user has collateral, the protocol can also choose to open debt instead. Who Receives Flash-Loan Revenue? The answer is: all depositors. After the flash loan finishes, the protocol updates the deposit interest index, which means the premium is ultimately distributed to liquidity providers.
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 _reserves[vars.currentAsset].updateState(); // Accrue premium into reserve income _reserves[vars.currentAsset].cumulateToLiquidityIndex( IERC20(vars.currentATokenAddress).totalSupply(), vars.currentPremium ); // Update annualized rates _reserves[vars.currentAsset].updateInterestRates( vars.currentAsset, vars.currentATokenAddress, vars.currentAmountPlusPremium, 0 ); // Transfer tokens back IERC20(vars.currentAsset).safeTransferFrom( receiverAddress, vars.currentATokenAddress, vars.currentAmountPlusPremium ); One subtle difference from Uniswap is that in AAVE the final token transfer happens from inside the AAVE contract after the user contract finishes executing. The user contract does not proactively send the tokens back to AAVE.
  </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: Interest Rate Code Walkthrough</title><url>/post/aave/aave-interest-update-code/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Compound</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>interest-model</tag></tags><content type="html">  Several parameters inside the AAVE interest-rate model interact with one another in fairly complex ways. Stable-rate borrowing is especially tricky, and the formula for the average stable rate is particularly hard to read. In real lending markets, however, many assets do not even support stable-rate borrowing, and among the assets that do, the share of stable-rate debt is very small, often well below 1%. So for beginners, it is completely reasonable to skip the stable-rate part on a first pass.
There are a few points worth highlighting in AAVE&amp;amp;rsquo;s interest-rate logic:
AAVE accrues interest based on timestamps, while Compound accrues interest based on block numbers. In both protocols, rate updates are triggered by actions such as deposit, withdraw, borrow, and repay, and they are only meaningfully updated once per block. Deposit interest grows linearly, while borrowing interest grows in compound form, i.e. exponentially over time. A percentage of borrowing income, the reserve factor …  </content></entry><entry><title>Next-Generation Matching Engine: A Message-Driven Parallel Matching Engine</title><url>/post/matching-engine/next-generation-matching-engine--parallel-matching-engine-base-on-message/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>Matching-engine</category></categories><tags><tag>Matching-engine</tag><tag>Matching</tag><tag>matching</tag><tag>matching-engine</tag><tag>parallel-matching</tag><tag>kafka</tag><tag>message-queue</tag><tag>exchange</tag><tag>CLOB</tag></tags><content type="html">  Centralized exchanges rely on a CLOB, or central limit order book, for matching. The matching rules are simple: price priority first, time priority second. For an exchange, the matching engine is foundational infrastructure. It must be stable, efficient, scalable, and fault-tolerant, and it must be able to recover or roll back quickly during extreme market conditions or system failures.
Message-Driven Parallel Matching This article proposes a message-driven parallel matching engine. &amp;amp;ldquo;Message-driven&amp;amp;rdquo; means the matching engine accepts only one kind of input: a message queue such as Kafka. The second part is the key question: what exactly is parallel matching?
Parallel matching means multiple machines match orders at the same time. It is not a single primary with N replicas, and it is not round-robin scheduling. It is true simultaneous matching. The obvious concern is whether this causes state inconsistency. The answer is that the persistence layer, including Redis and the …  </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: The Proxy System</title><url>/post/aave/how-aave-proxy/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Compound</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>smart-contract-proxy</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  Smart Contract Proxies Upgradeable smart contracts rely heavily on proxy patterns, and AAVE&rsquo;s proxy system is quite complex. To really understand it, you need to unpack it layer by layer.
Global AAVE proxy diagram:
According to OpenZeppelin&rsquo;s proxy model, smart contract proxies are commonly divided into two kinds: transparent proxies and UUPS proxies.
Today, OpenZeppelin generally recommends the UUPS approach because it is more lightweight and easier to work with.
LendingPoolAddressesProvider The first contract to understand is LendingPoolAddressesProvider, which sits at the center of the system. It acts both as a registry and as a management contract. It mainly serves two purposes:
create, upgrade, and manage other contracts act as a registry of addresses so other contracts can look up one another through it Several core contracts are created, upgraded, initialized, and managed through this contract:
LENDING_POOL LENDING_POOL_CONFIGURATOR Its name already gives away one of its main responsibilities: providing addresses. The following addresses are configured through LendingPoolAddressesProvider:
LENDING_POOL LENDING_POOL_CONFIGURATOR LENDING_POOL_COLLATERAL_MANAGER POOL_ADMIN EMERGENCY_ADMIN PRICE_ORACLE LENDING_RATE_ORACLE How does LendingPoolAddressesProvider actually create and manage contracts? The rough flow is:
When needed, it deploys a proxy template and sets the concrete implementation behind it. The core contracts listed above each store an addressesProvider variable. During initialization, they receive the provider address as a parameter. When those contracts need to call one another, they first query the other party&rsquo;s address through addressesProvider, and then perform the call. The code for creating or upgrading a proxy-backed contract looks like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 // Upgrade or create a contract function _updateImpl(bytes32 id, address newAddress) internal { address payable proxyAddress = payable(_addresses[id]); InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy proxy = InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy(proxyAddress); bytes memory params = abi.encodeWithSignature(&#39;initialize(address)&#39;, address(this)); if (proxyAddress == address(0)) { // If the proxy does not exist, deploy it first and initialize it proxy = new InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy(address(this)); proxy.initialize(newAddress, params); _addresses[id] = address(proxy); emit ProxyCreated(id, address(proxy)); } else { // If it already exists, upgrade it proxy.upgradeToAndCall(newAddress, params); } } LendingPoolConfigurator LendingPoolConfigurator, together with LendingPoolAddressesProvider, is used to create proxies for:
AToken StableDebtToken VariableDebtToken The initialization code is:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 function _initTokenWithProxy(address implementation, bytes memory initParams) internal returns (address) { // Deploy proxy contract InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy proxy = new InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy(address(this)); // Point the proxy to the implementation and initialize it proxy.initialize(implementation, initParams); return address(proxy); } Upgrading those token contracts is done like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 function _upgradeTokenImplementation( address proxyAddress, address implementation, bytes memory initParams ) internal { InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy proxy = InitializableImmutableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy(payable(proxyAddress)); proxy.upgradeToAndCall(implementation, initParams); } Relationship diagram:
The broader takeaway is that AAVE layers its upgradeability. LendingPoolAddressesProvider manages the top-level core contracts, while LendingPoolConfigurator manages reserve-specific token proxies beneath that. That multi-level arrangement is one reason the proxy system feels more complicated than many simpler protocols.
  ]]></content></entry><entry><title>rate fee of loopback swap in uniswap</title><url>/post/uniswap/uniswap-loopback-swap-fee/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>uniswap</category></categories><tags><tag>uniswap</tag><tag>uniswap v2</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>arbitrage</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  The transaction fee of uniswap is derived from the identity of x * y = K. In a specific transaction scenario, such as a loopback transaction, our transaction cost can be far lower than the rated fee.
What is a loopback transaction The loopback transaction is a transaction in a transaction pair tokenA/tokenB, first exchange tokenA to get tokenB, and then immediately exchange the obtained tokenB back to tokenA.
The standard rate of uniswap v2 is 0.3%, then the cost of loopback transaction is 0.6%, this cost is quite high. If we are just to brush the transaction volume, we need an effective way to reduce Handling fees, loopback transactions are a very effective way.
Theoretical Derivation The following is our detailed derivation process. Assumptions are as follows:
dx: the number of tokenA entered r0: the reserve quantity of tokenA r1: The reserve quantity of tokenB dy: the amount of the first tokenA -&gt; tokenB swap ex: the second swap tokenB -&gt; the number of tokenA According to the formula of uniswap, the calculation is as follows:
1 2 3 4 5 6 dy = dx*997*r1/(1000*r0 + dx*997) R1 = r1-dy R0 = r0 + dx ex = dy*997*R0/(1000*R1 + dy*997) Substituting dy, after simplification, we can get:
1 ex = 997*997*dx*(r0+dx) / (1000*1000*r0 + 997*997*dx) Divide by dx at the same time:
1 ex/dx = 997*997*(r0+dx) / (1000*1000*r0 + 997*997*dx) Since ex is our tokenA quantity at the end of the final loopback transaction, dx is our tokenA input quantity, and 1-ex/dx is our handling fee ratio.
It can be seen from the above formula that the final loopback transaction ex is only related to the input dx and the reserve of tokenA, and the higher the ratio of the input number dx to tokenA reserve, the final result is The closer the ex/dx is to 1, the less the fee is paid.
Code calculation The test code is as following:
Filename: loopbackSwap.js
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 const BigNumber = require(&#39;ethers&#39;).BigNumber const e18 = BigNumber.from(&#39;1000000000000000000&#39;) const getAmountOut = (amountIn, r0, r1) =&gt; { const amountInWithFee = amountIn.mul(997) , numerator = amountInWithFee.mul(r1) , denominator = r0.mul(1000).add(amountInWithFee); return numerator.div(denominator) } const getAmountBack = (amtIn, r0, r1, printable = false) =&gt; { const out = getAmountOut(amtIn, r0, r1) r0 = r0.add(amtIn) r1 = r1.sub(out) const dx = getAmountOut(out, r1, r0) if (printable) { console.info(&#39;swap x-&gt;y: out=%s r0=%s r1=%s backx=%s&#39;, out.toString(), r0.toString(), r1.toString(), dx.toString()) } return {amtInter: out, amtOut: dx} } function loopbackSwap() { const reserveA = BigNumber.from(1000000).mul(e18) , reserveB = BigNumber.from(2000000).mul(e18) , ratio = (multor) =&gt; reserveA.mul(multor).div(1000) let amts = [ 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 50, 100, 200, 500, 1000, 2000, 3000, 5000, 10000] for (let amt of amts) { let amtIn = ratio(amt) let {amtOut} = getAmountBack(amtIn, reserveA, reserveB) console.info(&#39;dx/reserve=%s amtOut/amtIn=%s&#39;, amt/1000, amtOut.mul(10000).div(amtIn).toNumber()/10000) } } loopbackSwap() run the scripts:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 npx hardhat run loopbackSwap.js dx/reserve=0.001 amtOut/amtIn=0.994 dx/reserve=0.002 amtOut/amtIn=0.994 dx/reserve=0.005 amtOut/amtIn=0.994 dx/reserve=0.01 amtOut/amtIn=0.994 dx/reserve=0.02 amtOut/amtIn=0.9941 dx/reserve=0.05 amtOut/amtIn=0.9942 dx/reserve=0.1 amtOut/amtIn=0.9945 dx/reserve=0.2 amtOut/amtIn=0.995 dx/reserve=0.5 amtOut/amtIn=0.9959 dx/reserve=1 amtOut/amtIn=0.9969 dx/reserve=2 amtOut/amtIn=0.9979 dx/reserve=3 amtOut/amtIn=0.9984 dx/reserve=5 amtOut/amtIn=0.9989 dx/reserve=10 amtOut/amtIn=0.9994 It can be seen from the results that when dx/reserve exceeds 1, the handling fee rate drops rapidly, and when dx/reserve=10, the handling fee is only 6/10000.
As a result, lightning loans can be used to lend a large amount of funds from the borrowing pool at a lower interest rate, and then perform loopback transactions. In some exchanges where transactions are mining, mining can be reduced in this way Handling fee, arbitrage profit.
Action Now, We can write a contract to execute our loopback transaction.
It should be noted that we cannot directly set the path parameter of uniswap router to [tokenA, tokenB, tokenA] for loopback transactions, but must be divided into two swaps, the first is [tokenA, tokenB] , then [tokenB, tokenA].
The sample code is as following:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 /// @dev swapLoopback swap tokenA to tokenB, then swap tokenB to tokenA /// @param _router uniswap-like router /// @param reward the reward token /// @param amountIn amount in /// @param amountOutMin just set to 0 /// @param path [tokenA, tokenB] function swapLoopback( address _router, // router address reward, // reward token uint amountIn, uint amountOutMin, address[] memory path ) public onlyOwner { address tokenIn = path[0]; uint tokenInitial = IERC20(tokenIn).balanceOf(address(this)); _approve(IERC20(tokenIn), address(_router)); // solhint-disable-next-line uint256 ts = block.timestamp + 60; uint[] memory amounts = IUniswapRouter(_router).swapExactTokensForTokens(amountIn, amountOutMin, path, address(this), ts); path[0] = path[1]; path[1] = tokenIn; // console.log(&#34;amounts:&#34;, amounts[1]); _approve(IERC20(path[0]), address(_router)); amounts = IUniswapRouter(_router).swapExactTokensForTokens(amounts[1], amountOutMin, path, address(this), ts); // other arbitrage code with reward.. reward; }   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>Meta Transactions and Their Implementation</title><url>/post/meta-transaction-and-implement/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>Solidity</category></categories><tags><tag>selector</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>EVM</tag><tag>ABI</tag><tag>Ethereum</tag><tag>EIP-712</tag><tag>meta-transaction</tag></tags><content type="html">  What Is a Meta Transaction? In simple terms, a meta transaction is a transaction submitted by a third party on behalf of the user.
The usual flow is:
The user constructs the transaction parameters and signs them. A third party sends the signed payload to a Relay or Forwarder contract. The Relay or Forwarder contract verifies the user&amp;amp;rsquo;s signature. The Relay or Forwarder contract calls the target contract. A normal transaction looks like this:
A meta transaction looks like this:
Note: the Relayer shown in the diagram is the Forwarder contract in this article.
What Can Meta Transactions Be Used For? Meta transactions are mainly useful in two areas:
User experience
The barrier to entry for decentralized applications is still high. To use a dapp, an ordinary user often has to: a. register on an exchange, deposit funds, complete KYC, and buy ETH b. install MetaMask, store a seed phrase safely, and learn how addresses work c. withdraw assets from the exchange d. understand how …  </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: The Interest Rate Model</title><url>/post/aave/aave-interest-model/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Compound</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag></tags><content type="html">  The interest-rate model and risk control are the core of any lending protocol. In AAVE, interest updates can be divided into three parts:
deposit interest variable borrow interest stable borrow interest As for risk control, I discuss that separately in a later article.
The ReserveData Struct ReserveData is the core data structure behind AAVE&amp;rsquo;s interest-rate mechanics. It is defined in contracts/protocol/libraries/types/DataTypes.sol:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 // refer to the whitepaper, section 1.1 basic concepts for a formal description of these properties. struct ReserveData { // stores the reserve configuration // multiple config values packed into a uint256 using bitmasks ReserveConfigurationMap configuration; // the liquidity index. Expressed in ray // deposit-side interest index: exchange rate between aToken and token uint128 liquidityIndex; // variable borrow index. Expressed in ray // variable-rate borrowing index uint128 variableBorrowIndex; // the current supply rate. Expressed in ray // weighted average of variable and stable borrowing uint128 currentLiquidityRate; // the current variable borrow rate. Expressed in ray // variable borrow rate uint128 currentVariableBorrowRate; // the current stable borrow rate. Expressed in ray // stable borrow rate uint128 currentStableBorrowRate; uint40 lastUpdateTimestamp; // tokens addresses address aTokenAddress; address stableDebtTokenAddress; address variableDebtTokenAddress; // address of the interest rate strategy address interestRateStrategyAddress; // the id of the reserve. Represents the position in the list of the active reserves uint8 id; } ReserveData is the most important structure in the lending relationship. Every asset that can be borrowed or supplied in the market has a corresponding ReserveData entry that records its key rate information.
The variables most directly related to interest are:
liquidityIndex: deposit interest index variableBorrowIndex: variable-rate borrowing index currentLiquidityRate: supply-side liquidity rate, used to update liquidityIndex currentStableBorrowRate: stable borrowing rate currentVariableBorrowRate: variable borrowing rate, used to update variableBorrowIndex Two-Slope Interest Rates At the core, interest rates are driven by supply and demand. Whenever available liquidity changes, AAVE adjusts rates automatically. In both AAVE and Compound, the variable used to express this supply-demand relationship is utilization. The definition is:
1 2 Utilisation = total borrows / (total deposits + total borrows) total borrows = variable borrows + stable borrows The rate curve looks like this:
The chart shows the behavior clearly:
When utilization is below the optimal utilization level, rate = base rate + utilization * slope1 When utilization exceeds the optimal level, rate = base rate + slope1 + (utilization - optimal utilization) * slope2 Once utilization moves past the optimal point, rates rise very quickly. That pushes borrowers to repay sooner, otherwise they risk being liquidated.
liquidityIndex This is the deposit-side index that describes the token/aToken exchange relationship.
It is mainly used in:
Deposits
The user&amp;rsquo;s tokens are transferred into the protocol and aTokens are minted to the user.
The conversion is:
1 aToken amount = token amount / liquidityIndex Withdrawals
The user&amp;rsquo;s aTokens are transferred back and burned, and the corresponding amount of underlying tokens is returned.
1 token amount = aToken amount * liquidityIndex Because liquidityIndex keeps increasing over time, these two formulas are enough to derive deposit interest earned by the user.
variableBorrowIndex Variable-rate borrowing
When a user borrows, the system mints debt tokens to track the principal plus time-based interest accrual.
1 varDebtToken amount = token amount / variableBorrowIndex Variable-rate repayment
When the user repays, the amount owed is calculated as:
1 token amount = varDebtToken amount * variableBorrowIndex Liquidation
Liquidation is one of the most important parts of risk control, and I cover it separately in the risk-control article.
Stable Borrowing Stable borrowing is conceptually similar to variable borrowing, but with some important differences. Because stable borrowing usage is relatively low, I will skip a detailed analysis of it here.
Interest Rate Calculation Flow The main logic lives in contracts/protocol/lendingpool/DefaultReserveInterestRateStrategy.sol, in the function calculateInterestRates.
The rough flow is:
Total borrows = variable borrows + stable borrows Utilization = total borrows / (total deposits + total borrows) Calculate the variable and stable borrow rates. Both use a two-slope piecewise-linear formula. a. variable rate = base variable rate + utilization * variable slope1, plus slope2 if utilization is in the second segment b. stable rate = base stable rate + utilization * stable slope1 Weighted average borrow rate = (variable borrows * variable rate + stable borrows * average stable borrow rate) / total borrows The average stable borrow rate is an input parameter and is not calculated here. currentLiquidityRate = (weighted average borrow rate / total borrows) * utilization * (1 - reserve factor) You can see that currentLiquidityRate is the most complex variable in the chain. Its purpose is to drive the calculation of the deposit-side rate, i.e. liquidityIndex.
For the code-level analysis of these formulas, see the separate article on AAVE interest-rate code.
AAVE series:
Introduction to the AAVE lending protocol Overall AAVE code architecture AAVE interest-rate model AAVE interest-rate code walkthrough AAVE liquidation AAVE flash loans How AAVE decouples modules AAVE proxy pattern AAVE testing and deployment   </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: Overall Code Architecture</title><url>/post/aave/how-aave-interest-update/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>Dapp</tag><tag>Lend protocol</tag><tag>architecture</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  AAVE Architecture Overview AAVE is a lending protocol, so its core revolves around four major actions: deposit, borrow, repay, and liquidation. In my view, one major reason AAVE looks complex is the existence of stable-rate borrowing, which significantly increases the complexity of the interest-rate model. Without that feature, the overall design would be much easier to understand.
The high-level AAVE architecture looks like this:
Directory Structure and Files The contracts live mainly under the contracts directory, which is organized like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 ├─adapters // External contract adapters │ └─interfaces ├─dependencies // Base libraries, mostly adapted from OpenZeppelin │ └─openzeppelin │ ├─contracts │ └─upgradeability ├─deployments // Deployment-related code ├─flashloan // Flash loan modules │ ├─base │ └─interfaces ├─interfaces // Interface definitions ├─misc │ └─interfaces ├─mocks // Test-related contracts │ ├─attacks │ ├─dependencies │ │ └─weth │ ├─flashloan │ ├─oracle │ │ └─CLAggregators │ ├─swap │ ├─tokens │ └─upgradeability └─protocol // Core implementation ├─configuration ├─lendingpool ├─libraries │ ├─aave-upgradeability │ ├─configuration │ ├─helpers │ ├─logic │ ├─math │ └─types └─tokenization └─base If you combine the main codebase with the deployment scripts and mocks, AAVE has roughly 30 contracts:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 LendingPoolAddressesProvider = &#39;LendingPoolAddressesProvider&#39;, LendingPoolAddressesProviderRegistry = &#39;LendingPoolAddressesProviderRegistry&#39;, LendingPoolParametersProvider = &#39;LendingPoolParametersProvider&#39;, LendingPoolConfigurator = &#39;LendingPoolConfigurator&#39;, ValidationLogic = &#39;ValidationLogic&#39;, ReserveLogic = &#39;ReserveLogic&#39;, GenericLogic = &#39;GenericLogic&#39;, LendingPool = &#39;LendingPool&#39;, PriceOracle = &#39;PriceOracle&#39;, Proxy = &#39;Proxy&#39;, LendingRateOracle = &#39;LendingRateOracle&#39;, AaveOracle = &#39;AaveOracle&#39;, DefaultReserveInterestRateStrategy = &#39;DefaultReserveInterestRateStrategy&#39;, LendingPoolCollateralManager = &#39;LendingPoolCollateralManager&#39;, InitializableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy = &#39;InitializableAdminUpgradeabilityProxy&#39;, WalletBalanceProvider = &#39;WalletBalanceProvider&#39;, AToken = &#39;AToken&#39;, DelegationAwareAToken = &#39;DelegationAwareAToken&#39;, AaveProtocolDataProvider = &#39;AaveProtocolDataProvider&#39;, StableDebtToken = &#39;StableDebtToken&#39;, VariableDebtToken = &#39;VariableDebtToken&#39;, FeeProvider = &#39;FeeProvider&#39;, TokenDistributor = &#39;TokenDistributor&#39;, StableAndVariableTokensHelper = &#39;StableAndVariableTokensHelper&#39;, ATokensAndRatesHelper = &#39;ATokensAndRatesHelper&#39;, UiPoolDataProvider = &#39;UiPoolDataProvider&#39;, WETHGateway = &#39;WETHGateway&#39;, UniswapLiquiditySwapAdapter = &#39;UniswapLiquiditySwapAdapter&#39;, UniswapRepayAdapter = &#39;UniswapRepayAdapter&#39;, FlashLiquidationAdapter = &#39;FlashLiquidationAdapter&#39;, Mock contracts below MockAToken = &#39;MockAToken&#39;, MockAggregator = &#39;MockAggregator&#39;, WETHMocked = &#39;WETHMocked&#39;, SelfdestructTransferMock = &#39;SelfdestructTransferMock&#39;, MockStableDebtToken = &#39;MockStableDebtToken&#39;, MockVariableDebtToken = &#39;MockVariableDebtToken&#39;, MockFlashLoanReceiver = &#39;MockFlashLoanReceiver&#39;, MockUniswapV2Router02 = &#39;MockUniswapV2Router02&#39;, MintableERC20 = &#39;MintableERC20&#39;, MintableDelegationERC20 = &#39;MintableDelegationERC20&#39;, Lending Core The core lending system includes:
Interest-rate logic
AAVE moves most interest and validation logic into libraries under contracts/protocol/libraries/logic/, mainly:
GenericLogic.sol Calculates user account-level data.
ReserveLogic.sol The core of the core. It handles the main interest-related calculations.
ValidationLogic.sol This library performs safety checks for deposits, borrows, repayments, liquidations, transfers, stable/variable rate switching, and so on.
LendingPool
LendingPool is the main entry point for lending actions such as deposit, borrow, repay, and liquidation.
LendingPoolCollateralManager
Responsible mainly for liquidation handling.
DefaultReserveInterestRateStrategy
Defines how interest rates change through calculateInterestRates.
Tokenization In AAVE, both user deposits and user debt are recorded as tokens. In Compound, only deposits are tokenized; debt is not. Personally, I do not think debt strictly needs tokenization, but AAVE chose that design.
AToken
Deposit receipt token, similar to Compound&rsquo;s cToken. When a user deposits an asset, AAVE mints the corresponding aToken.
DelegationAwareAToken
An AToken variant that supports delegation-related behavior.
StableDebtToken
Token used to record stable-rate borrowing.
VariableDebtToken
Token used to record variable-rate borrowing.
Markets, Providers, and Configuration Management LendingPoolAddressesProvider LendingPoolAddressesProviderRegistry LendingPoolParametersProvider LendingPoolConfigurator Oracle The oracle layer provides the pricing inputs needed for borrowing power, liquidation, and other protocol decisions.
Helper Contracts AaveProtocolDataProvider Aggregates and precomputes data for frontend consumption.
UiPoolDataProvider Also aggregates and prepares data for frontends.
StableAndVariableTokensHelper Helper management contract for setting borrow-rate-related parameters across multiple assets.
WalletBalanceProvider Queries balance information. It is not strictly necessary because similar functionality can be built with multicall, but this contract offers a more targeted and often faster interface.
ATokensAndRatesHelper Helper contract for configuration updates.
Adapters The adapter layer mainly consists of Uniswap-related adapters:
UniswapLiquiditySwapAdapter UniswapRepayAdapter FlashLiquidationAdapter Proxy LendingPool proxy plus several additional upgradeable proxies throughout the system At first glance, this many contracts can feel overwhelming. The practical way to study AAVE is to start from the core, especially the interest-rate model and risk-control-related contracts. That narrows the focus to roughly 7 or 8 contracts and makes the codebase much easier to digest.
  ]]></content></entry><entry><title>About</title><url>/about/</url><categories/><tags/><content type="html">  铁叔 老年程序员，以代码为生计，正在为世界的去中心化事业而奋斗。
Older programmers, who coding for a living, and fighting for a decentralize world.
projects technology Rust golang C/C++ smart contract &amp;amp; solidity java/Spring frontend contract me Email: guotie.9#gmail.com
  </content></entry><entry><title>AAVE Source Code Analysis: Introduction to the AAVE Lending Protocol</title><url>/post/aave/brief-introduction-to-aave-protocol/</url><categories><category>Defi</category><category>AAVE</category></categories><tags><tag>AAVE</tag><tag>Compound</tag><tag>Defi</tag><tag>Solidity</tag><tag>Dapp</tag><tag>Lend protocol</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  Lending was one of the earliest major applications in DeFi. A lending protocol is a smart-contract system that allows users to deposit and borrow tokens. In that sense it resembles a bank: depositors place assets into a lending application, the application lends those assets to borrowers, and depositors earn interest over time. When a borrower&rsquo;s position becomes undercollateralized, liquidation is triggered. Anyone can participate in the liquidation process, and successful liquidators receive a reward. The liquidation system protects the solvency of the lending market and, in turn, the interests of depositors.
DeFi lending differs from banks in several important ways:
Interest calculation a. In DeFi lending, interest starts accruing from the block in which you deposit and stops at the block in which you withdraw. b. DeFi lending rates can fluctuate widely and are tightly linked to utilization, which can be roughly understood as borrowed funds divided by total available funds. Most protocols define thresholds where rates rise sharply once utilization becomes too high, which can be painful for borrowers. c. All borrowing is overcollateralized. There is no concept of unsecured credit lending.
Liquidation a. All deposits and loans in DeFi are transparent on-chain. b. The liquidation rules are fixed and explicit. c. Anyone can liquidate, and liquidators can earn substantial rewards, often around 10% of the liquidated amount. d. Because the data is public and the incentives are strong, the liquidation system can operate reliably.
Flash loans Flash loans are one of AAVE&rsquo;s most important innovations. A flash loan is not a bank-style instant loan. It means borrowing and repaying within the same blockchain transaction. For example, if an arbitrage opportunity appears but you do not have the capital, you can use a flash loan to borrow, execute the arbitrage, repay principal plus interest, and keep the profit.
Flash loans are also widely used in contract exploits, because they allow attackers to access much larger amounts of capital. Many recent attacks have used flash loans as the funding source.
Collateral types Banks can accept many kinds of collateral because they can evaluate assets off-chain. DeFi lending can only support a subset of tokens, because those assets need transparent pricing. Traditional asset appraisal is difficult to bring fully on-chain.
DeFi lending has gone through three major stages. The first stage was represented by MakerDAO, the second by Compound, and the third by AAVE.
There is no doubt that MakerDAO was the pioneer. Compound redesigned the interest-rate model, and nearly every later lending design built on top of Compound in one way or another. AAVE then became the most complete system. Its core lending model is similar to Compound&rsquo;s, but compared with Compound and MakerDAO, AAVE stands out in several ways:
AAVE&rsquo;s biggest innovation was introducing flash loans. From that point on, anyone pursuing on-chain arbitrage or certain attack strategies no longer needed to worry about capital. Flash loans are a uniquely on-chain advantage; there is no equivalent in traditional finance. AAVE also introduced stable-rate borrowing. Compound&rsquo;s rates fluctuate continuously with utilization. When utilization spikes, borrowing costs can rise sharply, which is painful for long-term borrowers. AAVE added a stable-rate option to address that need. AAVE&rsquo;s codebase is better written than Compound&rsquo;s. It is cleaner, more structured, more readable, and easier to maintain. AAVE is also safer. Its modular design, code quality, and testing are stronger. For example, when Cream Protocol suffered a major exploit and lost tens of millions of dollars, I could not help thinking that if it had forked AAVE instead, that specific attack likely would not have been possible. I discuss that in more detail later. Unlike the swap market, where Uniswap clearly dominates, lending is still closer to a three-way contest between MakerDAO, Compound, and AAVE. AAVE has an advantage in total deposits, Compound has the broadest user base, and MakerDAO has very strong locked value. All three have their strengths, and the gaps between them are not overwhelming. The real distance is between these three leaders and the many imitators. Without major innovation, it is hard for newcomers to challenge them.
Because AAVE is more complex than Compound, most lending protocols on chains like BSC and HECO historically forked Compound instead. Many of those teams optimized for fast launches and never deeply studied Compound itself, so once the products went live they hardly dared to change anything. In many cases the only visible change was renaming cTokens into various xTokens, because the main objective was token issuance and short-term fundraising rather than protocol design.
From a learning perspective, AAVE is an outstanding codebase, several levels above Compound in overall engineering quality. Even AAVE v1 was already well structured, and v2 improved on it further. In many respects it is exemplary:
The project structure is very clear. Interfaces, libraries, implementations, core modules, and adapters are all well separated. It has complete tests. It has complete deployment scripts. It has solid official documentation and whitepapers. It has mature surrounding SDKs and code examples. It follows a consistent coding style and comment style, and functions are well documented. It includes proper linting and code-quality checks. Its use of library patterns is exceptionally polished. The WETHGateway unifies ETH and token flows cleanly. In my view this is clearer than Uniswap&rsquo;s router, which exposes many ETH-specific entrypoints. Its proxy usage is textbook quality, even though OpenZeppelin later provided a more general-purpose proxy solution. The only project I would put in the same class is Uniswap. Uniswap also open-sourced its frontend, while AAVE did not, and that is one area where AAVE falls short.
This post is the introduction to a broader AAVE code-analysis series: 0. Introduction to the AAVE lending protocol
Overall architecture of the AAVE codebase The AAVE interest-rate model AAVE interest-rate code walkthrough AAVE risk control AAVE flash loans How AAVE decouples its modules The AAVE proxy pattern AAVE deployment   ]]></content></entry><entry><title>libuv and TCP Keepalive</title><url>/post/libuv-and-tcp-keepalive/</url><categories><category>c/c++</category></categories><tags><tag>libuv</tag><tag>tcp</tag><tag>TCP Keepalive</tag><tag>linux</tag></tags><content type="html"><![CDATA[  libuv and TCP Keepalive About Keepalive The keepalive discussed here is different from HTTP keepalive. Here we are talking about TCP-level keepalive. Its purpose is to detect network failures between two communicating machines when neither endpoint can immediately observe that the path has broken.
HTTP keepalive means adding a keep-alive header so the server does not close the TCP connection after a single request, allowing the same connection to be reused for later requests.
The Linux kernel documentation for TCP keepalive is here: http://tldp.org/HOWTO/TCP-Keepalive-HOWTO/usingkeepalive.html It defines:
1 2 3 4 5 6 tcp_keepalive_time the interval between the last data packet sent (simple ACKs are not considered data) and the first keepalive probe; after the connection is marked to need keepalive, this counter is not used any further tcp_keepalive_intvl the interval between subsequential keepalive probes, regardless of what the connection has exchanged in the meantime tcp_keepalive_probes the number of unacknowledged probes to send before considering the connection dead and notifying the application layer In simpler words:
1 2 3 4 5 6 tcp_keepalive_time If no data is received from the peer for N seconds, start probing the peer with keepalive packets. tcp_keepalive_intvl The interval, in seconds, between keepalive probes. tcp_keepalive_probes The number of probes to send before the connection is considered dead. So if no data arrives from the peer within tcp_keepalive_time, keepalive probing begins. A probe is then sent every tcp_keepalive_intvl seconds. If the peer still does not respond after tcp_keepalive_probes attempts, the connection is closed.
On Linux, you can inspect the system keepalive settings like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 [root@localhost ~]# cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/tcp_keepalive_time 1800 [root@localhost ~]# cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/tcp_keepalive_probes 9 [root@localhost ~]# cat /proc/sys/net/ipv4/tcp_keepalive_intvl 75 Keepalive Socket APIs You can enable and configure keepalive for a socket like this:
1. Enable keepalive 1 2 3 4 5 int on = 1; if (setsockopt(fd, SOL_SOCKET, SO_KEEPALIVE, &amp;on, sizeof(on))) { // log return -1; } 2. Set tcp_keepalive_time 1 2 3 4 5 int idle = 10; if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPIDLE, &amp;idle, sizeof(int)) &lt; 0) { // log return -1; } 3. Set tcp_keepalive_probes 1 2 3 4 5 int probes = 4; if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPCNT, &amp;probes, sizeof(int)) &lt; 0) { // log return -1; } 4. Set tcp_keepalive_intvl 1 2 3 4 5 int intvl = 1; if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPINTVL, &amp;intvl, sizeof(int)) &lt; 0) { // log return -1; } Keepalive in libuv The API that libuv exposes only lets you configure two things:
Enable keepalive Set tcp_keepalive_time The API is uv_tcp_keepalive, with the following signature:
1 2 int uv_tcp_keepalive(uv_tcp_t* handle, int enable, unsigned int delay) Enable / disable TCP keep-alive. delay is the initial delay in seconds, ignored when enable is zero. Its implementation looks like this:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30 31 32 33 int uv__tcp_keepalive(int fd, int on, unsigned int delay) { if (setsockopt(fd, SOL_SOCKET, SO_KEEPALIVE, &amp;on, sizeof(on))) return -errno; #ifdef TCP_KEEPIDLE if (on &amp;&amp; setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPIDLE, &amp;delay, sizeof(delay))) return -errno; #endif /* Solaris/SmartOS, if you don&#39;t support keep-alive, * then don&#39;t advertise it in your system headers... */ /* FIXME(bnoordhuis) That&#39;s possibly because sizeof(delay) should be 1. */ #if defined(TCP_KEEPALIVE) &amp;&amp; !defined(__sun) if (on &amp;&amp; setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPALIVE, &amp;delay, sizeof(delay))) return -errno; #endif return 0; } int uv_tcp_keepalive(uv_tcp_t* handle, int on, unsigned int delay) { int err; if (uv__stream_fd(handle) != -1) { err = uv__tcp_keepalive(uv__stream_fd(handle), on, delay); if (err) return err; } if (on) handle-&gt;flags |= UV_TCP_KEEPALIVE; else handle-&gt;flags &amp;= ~UV_TCP_KEEPALIVE; /* TODO Store delay if uv__stream_fd(handle) == -1 but don&#39;t want to enlarge * uv_tcp_t with an int that&#39;s almost never used... */ return 0; } From this code you can see that if uv__stream_fd(handle) is not available yet, libuv only sets a flag on the handle and does not actually apply delay. In other words, tcp_keepalive_time is only set after the connection has been fully established. If the connection is not established yet, the delay value is not applied.
If you also want to configure the other two values yourself, you need custom code. For example:
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 // // Configure the remaining keepalive parameters. // probes: maps to kernel tcp_keepalive_probes, i.e. how many probes to send // before closing the connection if there is still no response. // intvl: maps to kernel tcp_keepalive_intvl, i.e. interval between probes. // idle: maps to kernel tcp_keepalive_time. int set_keep_alive(const uv_handle_t* handle, int probes, int intvl, int idle) { int ret; uv_os_fd_t fd; ret = uv_fileno(handle, &amp;fd); if (ret &lt; 0) { return ret; } if (idle &gt; 0) { if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPIDLE, &amp;idle, sizeof(idle))) return -1; } // Set tcp_keepalive_intvl if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPINTVL, (const void *) &amp;intvl, sizeof(int)) &lt; 0 ) { return -1; } // Set tcp_keepalive_probes if (setsockopt(fd, IPPROTO_TCP, TCP_KEEPCNT, (const void *) &amp;probes, sizeof(int)) &lt; 0) { return -1; } return 0; } This function can only be called after the connection has been established, because only then does the handle have an underlying file descriptor and uv_fileno can succeed.
  ]]></content></entry><entry><title/><url>/post/matching-engine/02-matching-engine-details/</url><categories/><tags/><content type="html">  redis 高可用 redis 事务 orderbook 在 redis 中的存储 数据库结构及订单存储 撮合引起启动时初始数据，及同步验证 启动
异步 哪些可以异步，哪些必须顺序执行?
故障定位，故障解决 性能   </content></entry></search>